<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>https://slisovski.rbind.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://slisovski.rbind.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description></description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Simeon Lisovski, 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://slisovski.rbind.io/media/logo_hu75a97a6201f0bab971e1f6bac57d4d81_148382_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://slisovski.rbind.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Europe to India – A little investigated route of migratory birds</title>
      <link>https://slisovski.rbind.io/post/rosefinch/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://slisovski.rbind.io/post/rosefinch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editors’ Choice article&lt;/em&gt;: Lisovski, S., Neumann, R., Albrecht, T., Munclinger, P., Ahola, M.P., Bauer, S., Cepak, J., Fransson, T., Jakobsson, S., Jaakkonen, T., Klvana, P., Kullberg, C., Laaksonen, T., Metzger, B., Piha, M., Shurulinkov, P., Stach, R., Ström, K., Velmala, W. and Briedis, M. (2021), The Indo-European flyway: Opportunities and constraints reflected by Common Rosefinches breeding across Europe. J Biogeogr. 48:1255–1266. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/jbi.14085&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/jbi.14085&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the common rosefinch is still a rather exotic bird species. In the last decades the bird with its iconic song that is often rendered as “pleased to meet you” (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dibird.com/species/common-rosefinch/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;check it out yourself&lt;/a&gt;), has expanded its huge breeding range westwards, and we have seen small populations emerging at new sites in Europe. During my undergraduate studies, my friend and co-author Roland Neumann was investigating a population at the Baltic Sea Coast. Since very little was known about their routes and their destinations, he was catching and banding individuals with the hope to get resightings from their wintering sites or from any location during their migratory journey. Unfortunately, the massive efforts didn’t pay off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were thus super excited that, in collaboration with the Swiss Ornithological Institute and co-funded by the German Ornithologists’ Society, we could deploy light-level geolocators on male rosefinches in 2011. These devices were still somewhat new in the sense that they have just gotten small enough to use on a 25g bird such as the common rosefinch. Those so called geolocators record light intensity that can be used after recapture and download of the data in the following year, to approximate their migratory journeys. At the same time, we were in close contact with colleagues from Czechia also working on this species and equally thrilled to deploy these loggers on some of the individuals from their Bohemian Mountain populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fieldwork went exceptionally and we had almost an entire year to make plans for the next field season in which we needed to especially look out for returning birds with geolocators, recapture them and retrieve the data containing so much information and the answer to our main questions of the birds’ whereabouts outside the breeding season. Both in northern Germany and in Czechia, we recaptured around 30% of the individuals (a reasonable return rate and the sample size we hoped for) just to learn that none of the devices recorded any data! Obviously, quite a downer that required some time to digest and to even think about rosefinch migration again. Yet, we decided to give it another go and repeat the study in 2013. This time we succeeded and collected useful data from several individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Fig01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&#34;&gt;Roland Neumann and Benjamin Metzger banding and measuring common rosefinches in the dunes of the Baltic Sea in Germany (left). Tomas Albrecht and Jaroslav Cepak preparing their mobile lab after a successful catch of rosefinches in the mountains of Bulgaria (right). (Photo credit: Simeon Lisovski, Pavel Munclinger)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, we learned that other research groups from across Europe were also collecting migration data from rosefinches. Colleagues from Finland deployed geolocators on males breeding as far north as Oulu (65°N), a Swedish research team collected tracks from males in southern Sweden, and besides the German and Czech data, Bulgarian colleagues were also successful in tracking rosefinches from their southern European breeding site (41°N). Since all of us were dealing with rather small sample sizes (3-10 tracks), we were all easily convinced and excited to pool the data allowing us to not only investigate population specific migration pattern in isolation but extend our objectives towards a flyway wide approach. Now, we saw the opportunity to identify general migration routes, bottlenecks as well as barriers on the so far understudied Indo-European flyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired, by previous large-scale research on the effects of wind on bird migration (Kranstauber et al. 2015 Ecology Letters) we constructed simple theoretical migration models that optimized the routes with respect to wind and resource availability during migration. These theoretical tracks revealed interesting patterns with seasonally specific bottlenecks such as the areas south of the Caspian Sea during spring migration. The comparison between the theoretical tracks and the collected empirical tracks also showed that rosefinches seem to make use of the straighter winds from India to Europe during spring, probably allowing for fast and direct migration to the breeding sites, while engaging in larger detours during autumn following the routes that provide highest security in terms of resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, this study shows how valuable even small and local studies can be, if seen as puzzle pieces helping to reveal the larger picture. Obviously, this needs an open and collaborative network of researchers which I am very glad to have encountered during this project. I would like to thank all of my co-authors for sharing not only their data but for providing their insights into the study systems, for fruitful discussion, for pushing me hard to explain the modeling approach and forcing me to meet empirical fieldwork and theory halfway!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Light‐Level Geolocator Analyses: A user&#39;s guide</title>
      <link>https://slisovski.rbind.io/post/geolocationuserguide/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://slisovski.rbind.io/post/geolocationuserguide/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Established in 1987, the ARGOS system allowed the world-wide tracking of animals equipped with satellite transmitters. This new technology provided unprecedented insights into the movements of animals. But the devices were bulky as well as heavy and not yet ready to track the majority of smaller species like birds. In search for alternatives, the biologist Rory Wilson recalled that early voyagers did not have on-board GPS, nor satellite transmitters to ascertain their position (1). Instead, they observed the sun`s trajectory to estimate their whereabouts, using the day length to derive latitude and the exact time of noon to estimate longitude. He concluded that a simple light sensor, which requires far less power than a satellite transmitter, may provide reliable information about seabird movements across the annual cycle. After designing tags that consisted of a light sensor, a clock, a memory chip, and a lithium battery, he first deployed these tags on wandering albatrosses and Magellanic penguins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, geolocation by light has come a long way and is currently one of the most frequently used tracking technologies in bird migration research. A real boost in the number of applications happened after Bridget Stutchbury and her team deployed 1.5g geolocators developed by the British Antarctic Survey on different songbird species in 2008 (2). Recently, Migrate Technology Ltd. developed a 0.32g logger that successfully recorded a 13.000km migration route of 10g Willow warblers from Far East Russia to East Africa (3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Fig1.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&#34;&gt;Figure 1: One of the first light-level geolocators deployed on an animal, a Magellanic penguin, to track its movement. The tag was developed, built and deployed by Rory Wilson, despite huge amount of flack for this approach criticising that this method was only good for revealing movement on an ocean basin scale. One of the most recent developed tag weights only 0.35 g (from Migrate Technology Ltd.) and was used to track a 10 g Willow warbler (right). Image credits: Rory Wilson (left, centre), Harald Ris (right).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there was not only the need to build smaller and smaller tags, but to develop tools and methods that produce scientifically sound and reproducible tracks from light intensity recordings. The major downside of this technology is arguable the low accuracy compared to satellite mediated locations that results from the fact that light almost never hits the sensor of the logger without some level of shading. And even worse, the very same amount of shading has a very different effect on the accuracy depending on the time of the year and the actual location of the logger on the globe. Thus, researcher regularly struggled in the analysis and interpretation of the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2011 the Swiss Ornithological Institute organised a first international workshop, at a beautiful site in the Alps, to discuss methods and potential developments of open source tools for the analysis of geolocator data. The National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis funded another meeting in 2013 taking place in Santa Barbara, California. Stimulated or improved by these meetings, various R packages and other open source tools emerged that allow users to apply different theories and use additional information to improve the accuracy and precision of location estimates based on light recordings.
In our &amp;lsquo;HOW TO&amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo; paper that is part of the special issue on biologging in Journal of Animal Ecology (Lisovski et al. 2020) we now provide an overview of the different tools that may help in choosing an appropriate analysis method. Furthermore, we give advice on how to interpret and report results and introduce a comprehensive online manual that applies the concepts to several datasets, demonstrates the use of open‐source analysis tools with step‐by‐step instructions and code and details our recommendations for interpreting, reporting and archiving &lt;a href=&#34;https://geolocationmanual.vogelwarte.ch/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Fig2.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&#34;&gt;Figure 2: Coding jam at the 1st international workshop on how to best analyse light level geolocator data to ensure sound and reproducible results (left). Michael Sumner guide to geolocation by light (right): Photo credit: Felix Liechti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even though satellite tags are becoming smaller and smaller too, allowing to track small birds with high accuracy, we consider our efforts to be of value to the research community for the years to come. In addition to the relatively low costs, several recent technological advancements will perhaps even increase the appeal of light level geolocators. The most important among them is probably the combination of light recording with other en-route data, such as air pressure, acceleration, magnetism and temperature. These additional data can facilitate the refinement of location estimates. For instance, acceleration data or changes in air pressure can distinguish movement and residency periods relatively easily, and such prior knowledge can then be fed into the stationary location estimation. These additional sensor data also provide a wealth of complementary information on fine‐scale behaviour: air pressure and temperature can be used to infer flight altitude and initiation and termination of migratory or foraging flights; acceleration data can be used to determine daily activity budgets and, given supplementary measurements, be related to energy expenditure and energy budgets; magnetic field data can be used to infer strategies in orientation and navigation during migration. Combining such behavioural information with refined, reliable and accurate location estimates can assist in identifying habitat associations of migrants or their responses to evolutionarily novel factors such as artificial light at night, sensory pollution or wind farms. This knowledge will improve our understanding of the fates of migrants and the bottlenecks they might experience at sensitive times and places, which will allow us to improve our conservation and management strategies for migratory populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;link to the online user guide: &lt;a href=&#34;https://geolocationmanual.vogelwarte.ch/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://geolocationmanual.vogelwarte.ch/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original publication:&lt;/strong&gt; Lisovski, S., Bauer, S., Briedis, M., Davidson, S.C., Dhanjal-Adams, K.L., Hallworth, M.T., Karagicheva, J., Meier, C.M., Merkel, B., Ouwehand, J., Pedersen, L., Rakhimberdiev, E., Roberto-Charron, A., Seavy, N.E., Sumner, M.D., Taylor, C.M., Wotherspoon, S.J. &amp;amp; E.S. Bridge (2019) Light-Level Geolocator Analyses: A user’s guide. Journal of Animal Ecology. &lt;a href=&#34;https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/1365-2656.13036&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) Grémillet 2015 Research Gate. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/283091193_Let_there_be_light_-_My_personal_account_of_how_Rory_P_Wilson_invented_seabird_geolocation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;
(2) Stutchbury et al. 2009 Science. [link](DOI: 10.1126/science.1166664)
(3) Sokolovskis et al. 2018 Movement Ecology. &lt;a href=&#34;https://movementecologyjournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s40462-018-0138-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How our ‘Avian Athlets’ could spread influenza</title>
      <link>https://slisovski.rbind.io/post/virusstints/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://slisovski.rbind.io/post/virusstints/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The migration of these small birds is fraught with difficulties, and most species will stop along the way to refuel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most common stop-over sites are in South-east Asia and along the Yellow Sea, areas where highly pathogenic avian influenza is now endemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us will have heard the term ‘bird flu’ at some point in the last decade, most likely due to concerns surrounding human infections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bird flu, which is the colloquial name for highly pathogenic avian influenza (HPAIV), isn’t in the news that much anymore, but that doesn’t mean it has disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2001, efforts to control HPAIV H5N1 have resulted in the destruction of over 400 billion chickens, with a significant socioeconomic cost to farmers and industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, a new strain of HPAIV – H5N8 – emerged in Asia, and with the migration of wild birds it has rapidly spread to Europe and North America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet another strain emerged in 2016, again rapidly spreading with wild birds, recently causing devastating outbreaks as far away as South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, there has been no outbreak of these viruses in Australia. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few ideas. The main one is that Australian ducks tend not to migrate beyond the Australian-Papuan area; it’s ducks that have been implicated in the spread of H5N8 and H5N6 to Europe and North America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But ducks aren’t the only birds who act as hosts for avian influenza – shorebirds can too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our study, published in the journal &lt;em&gt;Emerging Infectious Disease&lt;/em&gt;, we wanted to understand whether shorebirds that spend the summer months in Australia are being infected with HPAIV when they weren’t in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this, at the Peter Doherty Institute for Infection and Immunity, we tested two species – the incredible Tim Tam biscuit sized migratory shorebird called the Red-necked Stint, and a common Australian duck species called the Pacific Black Duck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of a long term collaboration with the Victorian Wader Study Group, Field and Game Australia with students from Deakin University, between 2011 and 2018, we collected over 1,500 blood samples from Red-necked Stint and 400 blood samples from Pacific Black Ducks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tested these samples for general influenza antibodies, as well as antibodies against specific strains of influenza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that our long-distance migrator, the Red-necked Stint, did have antibodies against HPAIV. These were particularly found in blood samples collected since 2014 and the emergence of H5N8 and H5N6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./map.png&#34; alt=&#34;png&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&#34;&gt;Figure 1: The migration routes of Red-necked Stints have substantial overlap with areas where HPAIV is endemic. Credit Simeon Lisovski as part of ongoing projects with the Victorian Wader Study Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These antibodies tell us that the birds were infected with highly pathogenic influenza and that their immune system generated a response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, there is no evidence that they still carry the virus when they arrive in Australia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with analysing antibodies is that we don’t know when or where these birds were infected. To make sure they weren’t infected in Australia, we tested local ducks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If these viruses were in Australia, local ducks would definitely have antibodies against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/eid/article/25/10/19-0699-f2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Our study&lt;/a&gt; found no evidence of these antibodies in the ducks and so we believe that Red-necked Stints are being infected somewhere in their migration outside Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This finding is important for two reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, if these highly pathogenic viruses were to make it to Australia, we now know it could be on the wings of shorebirds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction of HPAIV would have huge ramifications for the local poultry industry; there is currently a nationwide wild bird surveillance program in place for detection .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, most shorebird species are in a dramatic decline, and recovery plans are in place for many species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disease is often not included in these plans, but the results of our study strongly indicate that these birds are exposed to HPAIV, potentially adding to the decline of these amazing avian athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study was completed in collaboration with Deakin University, the CSIRO Australian Animal Health Laboratory, and the Australian Commonwealth Government Department of Agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pursuit.unimelb.edu.au/articles/how-our-avian-athletes-could-spread-influenza&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt; to original blogpost.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mitigating conflicts between agriculture and migratory geese: is shooting a viable option or just passing on the problem?</title>
      <link>https://slisovski.rbind.io/post/huntingmodel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://slisovski.rbind.io/post/huntingmodel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Following the recent article, Shooting may aggravate rather than alleviate conflicts between migratory geese and agriculture, Silke Bauer explains why management plans for migratory goose populations need to be considered across a broader scale.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A challenge with developing management plans for migratory populations is that these populations use several sites in their annual cycle. Therefore, local actions may not only affect how migratory animals behave and forage locally, but also when they move to another site, and how they behave and forage when there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike many other migratory species, most migratory goose populations have thrived in recent decades and massively increased their abundances. One reason behind these increases is probably their switch to agricultural food, which is abundantly available over long periods in the year. However, this use of agricultural resources frequently leads to conflicts with farmers. Control and management measures are therefore called for that have the shared objective of reducing these conflicts but still maintaining migratory populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./huntinggif2.gif&#34; alt=&#34;gif&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&#34;&gt;Figure 1: Model predictions for the migration of White-fronted geese in the default case (left panel), with predation risk increased by a factor of 10 (middle panel) or 100 (right panel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geese are interacting with humans on various sites along the flyway. In the wintering area, they are left undisturbed or are increasingly shot for management purposes, while on most migratory sites geese are a quarry species. For example, in Russia geese are hunted mainly during spring migration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used a theoretical approach – a behaviour-based migration model – to assess the consequences of derogation shooting, hunting and scaring on the migration behaviour and demographic rates of geese, and how these accumulate in agricultural damage. We applied this model to the Baltic-North Sea population of white-fronted geese (Anser albifrons), which has increased from 10,000-50,000 in the 1950s to 1,200,000 around 2010, raising serious conflicts with agriculture, particularly in the Netherlands where the majority of these geese overwinter. We were particularly interested in whether such actions would alleviate conflicts with agriculture or pass on the problem to other sites. We ran scenarios with shooting/hunting being installed at single or multiple locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./geese-helmut-kruckenberg.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&#34;&gt;Figure 2: White-fronted geese. © Helmut Kruckenberg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that hunting, shooting and scaring can result in a suite of direct and indirect consequences on migration and foraging behaviour – from less intense foraging and later migratory departure, to avoiding sites. Most importantly, changing conditions on a particular site, be it through management or natural processes, not only alters the behaviour of migrants immediately and locally, but could also do so at a later time and at a distance. Furthermore, the specific consequences of shooting/hunting could be counter-intuitive, i.e. aggravate rather than alleviate agricultural damage, depending on where along the migration route changes had taken place and the mechanisms through which hunting/shooting was assumed to affect geese. This means that although local management actions can be effective locally, i.e. chase geese away or force them to migrate earlier, these might pass on the problem to sites further down the flyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While our modelling approach made several simplifying assumptions and can only be a first step in developing an adaptive management plan, our results do underline that management plans for migratory geese should be formulated and evaluated on a flyway level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the full article, &lt;a href=&#34;https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1365-2664.13152&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Shooting may aggravate rather than alleviate conflicts between migratory geese and agriculture&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Journal of Applied Ecology&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://appliedecologistsblog.com/2019/08/27/senior-editor-vacancy-apply-now/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt; to original blogpost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://slisovski.rbind.io/publication/bauer_et_al_2018-japplecol/&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt; to article download.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://slisovski.rbind.io/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://slisovski.rbind.io/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
